# Rituraj Singh

Curriculum Vitae



Address North of Azad Chowk, Gangjala, Saharsa, Bihar, India

Phone (+91) 9955151033

Email riturajsingh.infotech@gmail.com

Google Scholar Rituraj Singh

Website https://devrituraj.github.io/

Languages English (fluent), Maithili (native), Hindi (fluent), Bengali (beginner), French (beginner).

## RESEARCH AREAS

My research focuses on developing algorithms for machine learning, mainly focused on unsupervised, semisupervised learning, and knowledge graphs. I am passionate to apply machine learning methods in domains as Natural Language Processing, Human in the loop Systems, Healthcare in quest to streamline the traditional domains. My area of interests are Machine Learning, Bayesian Learning, Deep Learning, Human-in-the-loop AI, Crowdsourcing, Workflows, and in broad Artificial Intelligence.

# **EDUCATION**

### PhD in Computer Science & Engineering

2018-2021

- INRIA IRISA University de Rennes 1, France
  - Co-advised by Dr. Loïc Hélouët and Dr. Zoltán Miklós
  - Thesis: Data Centric Workflows for Crowdsourcing Applications.

#### M.Tech in Computer Science & Engineering

2013-2015

- Indian Institute of Technology, Patna, India.
  - Advised by Dr. Ashok Singh Sairam
  - Thesis: Push based User Selection in Crowdsensing.

#### B.Tech. in Information Technology

Rajasthan Technical University, Rajasthan, India.

2008-2012

# WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Full time Researcher

Oct 2021-now

TCS Research, Pune, India

• Research focus in on building analytics-based tools for automatic candidate evaluation. Research areas - Natural Language Processing, Knowledge graphs

Researcher 2015-2017

TCS Research and Innovation Labs, Kolkata, India

Research on applying machine learning models on sensor and wearable healthcare data. The work led to several
publications and patents.

Internship Summer 2014

TCS Research and Innovation Labs, Kolkata, India

• Project on anomaly detection using unsupervised learning in Smart meter sensor data.

## RESEARCH INTERESTS

Machine Learning, Bayesian Learning, Deep Learning, Human-in-the-loop AI, Crowdsourcing, Workflows, and in broad Artificial Intelligence.

# **PATENTS**

- 5. Soma Bandyopadhyay, Arijit Ukil, Rituraj Singh, Puri Chetanya, Arpan Pal, CA Murthy, "Anomaly detection by self-learning of sensor signals", Patent No.: US 10,743,821 B2
- 4. Sahu Ishan, Ayan Mukherjee, Arijit Ukil, Soma Bandyopadhyay, Puri Chetanya, Rituraj Singh, Arpan Pal, Rohan Banerjee, "Method and system for joint selection of a feature subset-classifier pair for a classification task", Pub. No.: US 2019/0361919 A1
- 3. Soma Bandyopadhyay, Arijit Ukil, Puri Chetanya, Rituraj Singh, Arpan Pal, C A Murthy, "Method and system for pattern recognition in a signal using morphology aware symbolic representation", Pub. No.: US 2019/0278971 A1
- Soma Bandyopadhyay, Arijit Ukil, Puri Chetanya, Rituraj Singh, Arpan Pal, C A Murthy, "Systems and methods for detecting anomaly in a cardiovascular signal using hierarchical extremas and repetitions", Pub. No.: US 2019/0200935 A1
- Arijit Ukil, Soma Bandyopadhyay, Puri Chetanya, Rituraj Singh, Arpan Pal, "Generalized one-class support vector machines with jointly optimized hyperparameters", Pub. No.: US 2019/0050690 A1
   Note: For complete list, please visit Google Scholar page.

# RESEARCH PUBLICATIONS

- 7. Rituraj Singh, Loïc Hélouët, Zoltán Miklós, "Reducing the Cost of Aggregation in Crowdsourcing", Transactions on Large-Scale Data and Knowledge-Centered Systems.
- 6. Loïc Hélouët, Zoltan Miklos, Rituraj Singh, "Cost and Quality Assurance in Crowdsourcing Workflows", PetriNets 2021. (Authors listed in alphabetical order).
- 5. Rituraj Singh, Loïc Hélouët, Zoltán Miklós, "Reducing the Cost of Aggregation in Crowdsourcing", International Conference on Web Services (ICWS 2020).
- 4. Pierre Bourhis, Loïc Hélouët, Zoltán Miklós, Rituraj Singh, "Data Centric Workflows for Crowdsourcing", 41st International Conference on Application and Theory of Petri Nets and Concurrency, (PetriNets) 2020. (Authors listed in alphabetical order).
- 3. Arijit Ukil, Ishan Sahu, Chetanya Puri, Ayan Mukherjee, Rituraj Singh, Soma Bandyopadhyay, Arpan Pal, "AutoModeling: Integrated Approach for Automated Model Generation by Ensemble Selection of Feature Subset and Classifier", International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN) 2019
- 2. Arijit Ukil, Soma Bandyopadhyay, Chetanya Puri, Rituraj Singh, Arpan Pal, "Effective Noise Removal and Unified Model of Hybrid Feature Space Optimization for Automated Cardiac Anomaly Detection Using Phonocardiogarm Signals", IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2018.
- 1. Soma Bandyopadhyay, Arijit Ukil, Rituraj Singh, Chetanya Puri, Arpan Pal, CA Murthy, "Pattern Analysis in Physiological Pulsatile Signals: An Aid to Personalized Healthcare" 40th Annual International Conference of the IEEE Engineering in Medicine and Biology Society (EMBC) 2018

Note: For complete list, please visit Google Scholar page.

## **ACHIEVEMENTS**

- Fellowship ANR Headwork Project (2018).
- Scholarship GATE Masters Scholarship (2013-2015).
- Received "TCS i-Citation Award" (2016 & 2017).
- Part of team Winner Physionet Challenge (2017).
- All India Rank 440 (out of 224160 candidates) in Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE) 2013.

## TEACHING EXPERIENCE

## Travaux Pratiques<sup>1</sup> for Artificial Intelligence - Topics on Deep Learning

Spring 2021

• Graduate level introduction to Deep learning (Fully Connected Network, CNN, RNN, LSTM) using Tensorflow, Keras at ESIR — University of Rennes 1.

### Travaux Pratiques Data Mining Course

Spring 2019,2018

• Graduate level course on data mining using numpy, pandas, scipy, sklearn libraries at ESIR — University of Rennes 1.

#### Teaching Assistant for JAVA programming language

Fall 2014

• Undergraduate level course on JAVA programming - IIT Patna

## Teaching Assistant for Shell programming and C programming language

Spring 2013

• Undergraduate level course on Shell programming and C language - IIT Patna.

# COMPUTER SKILLS

- Programming languages: Python, Matlab, Java, C, C++, Android.
- Frameworks: Pytorch, Tensorflow
- Database Systems: MySQL, SPARQL.
- Scientific: LATEX, Git.

# **PROJECTS**

- Building tools for candidate evaluation.
- Data Centric Workflows for Complex Crowdsourcing Applications.
- Anomaly detection and its impact on disease classification on Bio-medical data.
- Crowdsensing using Mobile Phone.

Note: For further details on my research, please visit the publications page.

# EXTRA CURRICULUM ACTIVITIES

- Sports: Badminton, video-games, hiking.
- Hobbies: traveling, reading, movies, playing keyboard.

# REFERENCES

- 1. Dr. Loïc Hélouët, Chargé de recherche, SUMO Team, INRIA, Rennes, France.
- 2. Dr. Zoltán Miklós, Assistant Professor, Universite de Rennes 1, DRUID Team, IRISA, Rennes, France.
- 3. Dr. Ashok Singh Sairam, Associate Professor, Indian Institute of Technology, Guwahati, India.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>Equivalent to Teaching Assistant